Notice that besides RMW instructions
and semaphores, there are more
available synchronization mechanisms.
Linux for instance offers synchronization
primitives like mutex, condition variables,
monitors, and barriers, among others.
Which one to use is something that depends on the
application. For instance, if you have to choose
between an entry section that relies on spinning
or one that uses a Linux futex (which tries to
acquire a lock in the entry section but instead
of spinning puts the thread in the waiting queue),
you might want to consider how long the
critical section is. It might be OK to
spin and "waste" CPU for a relatively short
critical section that happens sporadically,
but maybe not for a long one
that is executed frequently...
Windows too offers synchronization
primitives, for instance interrupt
masks to protect access to global resources
on uniprocessors and busy-wait spinlocks for
multiprocessors (we have discussed before why
disabling interrupts on a single processor might
be not enough to have valid solutions to the
critical section problem). Finally, it also
offers objects like mutexes, semaphores or to
provide events (similar to condition variables).
If we look at pthreads, you will see it also
offers synchronization mechanisms like mutex locks
with blocking queues, which can also
support fairness, condition variables,
and other non-portable extensions.
Notice that an OS that defines and offers
such synchronization primitives usually needs
such synchronization primitives itself, to protect
its shared variables when multiple
concurrent/parallel threads run the OS code!